# Summary

I am a seasoned Machine Learning Engineer specializing in Computer Vision (CV) with a strong interest in robotics. My expertise lies in deploying cutting-edge deep learning models for real-time object detection, segmentation, object tracking, and activity recognition, both on cloud and edge devices. I'm dedicated to driving innovation and success at the intersection of CV and robotics, pushing the boundaries of autonomous systems.

## **Professional Experience**

### Research Assistant, MAIM Lab

September 2024 – Present

University of Dhaka

 $Dhaka, \ Bangladesh$ 

• A 50 Million Dollar project of the "Welcome Leap In Utero" program. Working on Translation of a Wearable Fatal Movement Monitor towards Stillbirth Prevention. This is a collaborative work of "Imperial College of London", "University College Dublin" and "University of Dhaka"

## Data Scientist, Executive

January 2024 – August 2024

 $SSL\ Wireless$ 

Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Working in a dynamic environment to solve machine learning challenges
- Working as a primary developer for a CV project of a Multi-national client, overseeing from model development to deployment
- Contribute to multiple computer vision, OCR and ML based projects
- Attend corporate client meetings for clarification of client specific requirements

## Machine Learning Engineer

Headless Technologies Ltd.

February 2023 – October 2023

Dhaka, Bangladesh

- Collaboration with a multi-national team to develop and upgrade deep learning-based fall detection system.
- Manage software updates to add new features, close security holes and resolve defects.
- Deployment of state-of-the-art deep learning models and frameworks for activity recognition task

#### Machine Learning Intern

January 2023 - February 2023

Headless Technologies Ltd.

Dhaka, Bangladesh

• Received mentorship for handling state-of-the-art project and multi-national clients.

#### Education

## University of Dhaka, Bangladesh

January 2018 – March 2023

 $Bachelor\ of\ Science\ in\ Robotics\ \mathcal{E}\ Mechatronics\ Engineering$ 

CGPA: 3.30/4

- Fazlul Haque Muslim Hall Scholarship (Freshman year)
- 1st place in the Student project category in a poster competition at the seminar on "Robotics in Bangladesh: Academia and Industry Initiatives"

## **Projects**

Wheat Phenotyping | Python, Shellscript, PyTorch, MMDetection, PyQt5 Git

August 2022 – Ongoing

- A framework for providing various phenotyping tasks using Computer Vision
- Deep learning-based model inference for wheat yield estimation from field imaging

Portialyze Carevision | Python, Activity Recognition, PyTorch, YOLOv8, PyQt5 Website January 20

January 2023 - Ongoing

- Real-time image analysis and IoT cloud system using AI (Artificial Intelligence)
- Human Activity Recognition in real world using YOLOv8 and PoseC3D

STPT-based Activity Recognition | Python, PyTorch, MMAction2 Git

July 2023 - Ongoing

- Human activity recognition based on Spatio-Temporal Polychromatic Trajectory
- Unified framework for train, test and inference activity recognition DL models. gRPC server for object detection | Python, gRPC, protobuf, PyTorch, YOLO Git

March 2024

• A gRPC based server application that can handle both unary and streaming requests with images for object detection, using YOLOv8 model.

gRPC client for object detection | Python, gRPC, OpenCV Git

March 2024

• A Python client for communication with gRPC based server for both unary-unary and streaming object detection requests

## **Publications**

Batin, M. A., Islam, M., Hasan, M. M., Azad, A. K. M., Alyami, S. A., Hossain, M. A., Miklavcic, S. J. "WheatSpikeNet: An Improved Wheat Spike Segmentation Model for Accurate Estimation from Field Imaging." Frontiers in Plant Science, 14, 1226190. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2023.1226190

Batin, M. A., Islam, M., Hasan, M. M., Miklavcic, S. J. (2022). "Improved Detection and Analysis of Wheat Spikes U sing Multi-Stage Convolutional Neural Network." *Dhaka University Journal of Applied Science and Engineering*, 7(2), 21-30. https://doi.org/10.3329/dujase.v7i2.65090

## Skills

Communication: Bengali - Native, English - Proficient Programming Languages: Python, C/C++, Java

Libraries and Frameworks: PyTorch, Tensorflow, Pandas, Ultralytics, MMDetection, MMAction2

Database Management: MySQL, PostgreSQL, Milvus VectorDB

Software & Tools: Linux, Git, Docker, Jira, Google Colab, Jupyter Notebook, VSCode, PyCharm, Microsoft Excel

Typesetting: LaTex, Microsoft Word Hardware: Jetson Nano, Raspberry Pi

## References

#### • Dr. Md Mehedi Hasan

Assistant Professor, RME, University of Dhaka.

Email: mmhasan@du.ac.bd

Mobile (Dept):  $+88~02~9661900~{\rm Ext.}~8810$ 

Mobile (Personal): +8801707034821

#### • Tanmoy Basak Anjan

CTO, Headless Technologies Ltd. Email: tanmoy@headless.ltd

Mobile (Personal): +8801721010849

#### • Dr. Abhishek Kumar Ghosh

Assistant Professor, RME, University of Dhaka.

Email: abhishek.rme@du.ac.bd Mobile (Personal): +8801502908408

#### • Ashqar Mahi

Head of Data, SSL Wireless ashqar.mahi@sslwireless.com

Mobile (Personal): +8801678139821